Arlene Blum papers, M1558
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
Arlene Blum papers,
Bulk, 1960-1986
1920-2009 inclusive; 1960-1986 bulk
M1558
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
61.5 Linear feet (73 boxes, 10 cartons, 11 flat boxes, 1 map folder)
The Arlene Blum papers include photographs, writings, diaries, articles about the Annapurna expedition in 1978, a year-long trek across the Himalayas, and various other climbs. Also inlcuded are drafts of articles and books by Arlene Blum, photographs albums and writings of her father Ludwig Blum, school work, letters, etc.
Box 1
Biography
Arlene Blum (born March 1, 1945) is an American mountaineer, writer, and environmental health scientist. She is best known for leading an all-woman ascent of Annapurna, a climb that was also the first successful American ascent. In the early 1960s, she attended Reed College in Portland, Oregon. Blum graduated from Reed and attended MIT and UC Berkeley, where she earned a Ph.D. in biophysical chemistry in 1971.
Blum was part of the first all-woman team to ascend Alaska's Mount McKinley in 1970. She participated in a 1976 expedition up Mount Everest as part of the American Bicentennial Everest Expedition, but did not reach the summit. In 1978, she organized a team of thirteen women to climb Annapurna in Nepal which, until then, had been climbed by only eight people (all men). The first summit team, comprising Vera Komarkova and Irene Miller and Sherpas Mingma Tsering and Chewang Ringjing, reached the top at 3:30 p.m. on October 15, 1978. The second summit team, Alison Chadwick-Onyszkiewicz and Vera Watson, died during this climb. After the event, Blum wrote a book about her experience on Annapurna, called Annapurna: A Woman's Place.
She led the first expedition to climb Bhrigupanth in the Indian Himalayas, leading a team of Indian and American women. She then attempted what she called the "Great Himalayan Traverse," a two-thousand-mile journey across the treacherous but beautiful peaks of the Himalayas from Bhutan to India.
As a researcher at the University of California, Berkeley, in the late 1970s, Blum's research contributed to the regulation of two cancer-causing chemicals used as flame retardants on children's sleepwear. After a long hiatus, Blum returned to science and policy work in 2006—when her daughter started college—and her memoir Breaking Trail: A Climbing Life was published. She discovered that the same Tris her research had helped remove from children's pajamas was back in California couches and baby products. In 2007 Blum co-founded the Green Science Policy Institute (GSP) with the goal of bringing scientific research results into policy decisions to protect human health and the environment from toxic chemicals. As executive director of the Green Science Policy Institute, Blum and her team have led several successful national and international campaigns against the use of toxic chemicals. Blum has published articles about science policy in The New York Times, Los Angeles Times, The Huffington Post, and Science magazine.[Wikipedia]
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by Arlene Blum to Stanford University, Special Collections in three accessions from 2007 to 2010.
Scope and Contents note
Material in the Arlene Blum papers is arranged by accession and is divided into 4 series: Series 1. 2007 accession; Series 2. Accession 2010-099; Series 3. Accession 2010-021; and Series 4. Slides from the 2010-021 accession.
Series 1. 2007 accession contains materials relating to the American Women's Himalayan Expedition. Team member diaries are closed until 2028.
Series 2. Accession 2010-099 consists of two subseries: Arlene Blum materials and Ludwig Blum materials. Arlene's subseries contains school materials, letters, diaries, articles on climbs, etc. Ludwig Blum was Arlene's father and this subseries contains photographs and draft writings.
Series 3. Accession 2010-021 includes materials relating to the Annapurna expedition, Arlene's trek across the Himalayas, drafts of Annapurna: A Women's Place, drafts of "Women in High Places: A History of Women in Mountaineering" (unpublished), diaries, articles, etc.
Series 4. Slides (from accession 2010-021) consists primarily of images of climbs and treks. They are arranged alphabetically.
Access
Materials are open to research, except that diaries of individual climbers (Box 3) are closed until 1/1/2028 unless permission is granted by that individual.
American Women's Himalayan Expedition, Inc..; Annapurna Expedition, (1978).; Ashton, Marie.; Beardsley, Irene A.; Blum, Arlene, 1945-; Chadwick-Onyszkiewicz, Alison.; Firey, Joan.; Hoeman, Grace; Klobusicky-Mailaender, Liz.; Komarkova, Vera.; Miller, Irene; Rusmore, Margi.; Taylor, Dyanna.; Tews, Christy.; Watson, Vera.; Whitehouse, Annie.; Berkeley (Calif.); Diaries.; Everest, Mount (China and Nepal).; Himalaya Mountains; Mountaineering; Mountaineering--Nepal--Annapurna.; Photographs.; Slides.; Women mountaineers--United States; Women mountaineers.
- Series 1: 2007 accession: American Women's Himalayan Expedition, Annapurna ascent
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1. 2007 accession contains materials relating to the American Women's Himalayan Expedition. Team member diaries are closed until 2028 unless special permission is given by individual.
  - Team letters, 1972-1976 (Carton 14)
    - Arlene Blum letters, 1972-1976 (Carton 14)
    - Wanda, undated (Carton 14)
    - Irene Beardsley, 1974 (Carton 14)
    - Cherie Bremer-Kamp (Carton 14)
    - Alice Culbert (Carton 14)
    - Piro Kramar (Carton 14)
    - Fay Kerr and Margaret Clark (Carton 14)
    - Joan Firey (Carton 14)
  - Team letters, 1977-1979 (Carton 14)
    - Irene Beardsley (Carton 14)
    - Joan Firey (Carton 14)
    - Alison Chadwick-Onyszkiewicz (Carton 14)
    - Vera Komarkova (Carton 14)
    - Liz Klobusicky (Carton 14)
    - Piro Kramar (Carton 14)
    - Margi Rusmore (Carton 14)
    - Dyanna Taylor (Carton 14)
    - Christy Tews (Carton 14)
    - Vera Watson (Carton 14)
    - Annie Whitehouse (Carton 14)
  - Biographies of members (Carton 14)
  - Arlene Blum's Annapurna letters, 1977-1979 (Carton 14)
  - Logistics letters (Carton 14)
    - Contracts between members (Carton 14)
    - American Alpine Club (AAC) (Carton 14)
    - Mike Cheney Expedition Services - Sherpa Coop (Carton 14)
    - Sherpa Coop, continued (Carton 14)
    - Logistics on mountain (Carton 14)
    - Logistics letters: five spiral bound notebooks (Carton 14)
  - Base camp cables (Carton 14)
  - Letters on climb (Carton 14)
    - United States Embassy (Carton 14)
    - Family (Carton 14)
  - Friends and family (Carton 14)
    - Sherpas (Carton 14)
    - Friends and family (Carton 14)
    - Friends (Carton 14)
  - Vera Komarkova and Alison Chadwick-Onyszkiewicz tradegy (Carton 14)
    - Irene Beardsley and Colin Miller letters (Carton 14)
    - Alison Chadwick-Onyszkiewicz (Carton 14)
    - Alison Chadwick-Onyszkiewicz family letters (Carton 14)
    - Vera Komarkova (Carton 14)
  - Annapurna information (Carton 14)
    - Dutch expedition, 1977 (Carton 14)
    - Other expeditions (Carton 14)
    - Facts (Carton 14)
    - Photographs (Carton 14)
    - Expedition report after climb ( Kathmandu) (Carton 14)
  - Pre-climb preparation (Carton 14)
    - Pre-climb press (Carton 14)
    - Application (Carton 14)
    - Training trips (Carton 14)
    - Reconnaisance, 1977 (Carton 14)
    - Team information (Carton 14)
    - Budget (Carton 14)
    - Food (Carton 14)
    - Medical/Oxygen (Carton 14)
    - Psychology (Carton 14)
    - Equipment (Carton 14)
  - Logistics preparation (Carton 14)
    - Transportation (Carton 14)
    - On mountain (Carton 14)
  - Fundraising (Carton 14)
    - Miscellaneous fundraising (Carton 14)
    - Minutes and agendas (Carton 14)
    - Treks (Carton 14)
    - T-shirts (Carton 14)
  - Publicity
    - Publicity (Carton 14)
    - Documentary film (Carton 15)
    - American Women's Himalayan Expedition Annapurna climb - posters (Map-folder 4)
  - Book materials (Carton 15)
  - Legal (Carton 15)
  - Post climb (Carton 15)
    - Jimmy Carter - congratulation letter (Carton 15)
    - Press conference (Carton 15)
  - Annapurna miniseries (Metro Media) (Carton 15)
  - VWACO memorial fund ( Vera Watson; Alison Chadwick-Onyszkiewicz) (Carton 15)
  - RVHM (Rendez-Vous Hautes Montagnes) (Carton 15)
  - Chadwick correspondence, 1978-1979 (Carton 15)
  - Articles and clippings (Carton 15)
    - Post climb articles (Carton 15)
    - American Women's Himalayan Expedition Newsletters (Carton 15)
    - National Geographic (Carton 15)
    - Nepal Annapurna articles (Carton 15)
    - Annapurna writers (Carton 15)
    - Articles and clippings (3 of 3): loose clippings (Carton 15)
  - Articles
    - Los Angeles Times (Carton 15)
    - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1977-1981 (Carton 15)
    - Christian Science Monitor, People, Glamour (Carton 15)
    - Oakland Tribune, Palo Alto Times, Oregonian, San Jose Mercury News (Carton 15)
    - Articles about Arlene Blum, 1980-1986 (Carton 15)
    - New York Times (Carton 15)
  - American Women's Himalayan Expedition
    - Letter from Captain Damber Gurung to Arlene Blum (Nepal) (Carton 15)
    - American Women's Himalayan Expedition, Annapurna I, sherpas (Carton 15)
    - American Women's Himalayan Expedition, Annapurna I, film party (Carton 15)
    - American Women's Himalayan Expedition, Annapurna I, stores and equipment (Carton 15)
    - American Women's Himalayan Expedition, Annapurna I, bank and finance, insurance, 1978 (Carton 15)
  - Team Diaries (photocopies)
    Access
    Diaries are closed until 1/1/2028 unless permission is granted from individual.
    - Christy Tews (Box 16)
    - Liz Klobusicky (Box 16)
    - Dyanna Taylor (Box 16)
    - Annie Whitehouse (Box 16)
    - Arlene Blum (Box 16)
    - Vera Komarkova (Box 16)
    - Irene Beardsley (Box 16)
    - Margi Rusmore (Box 16)
    - Joan Firey (Box 16)
    - Marie (Box 16)
- Series 2: Accession 2010-099
  Series 2. Accession 2010-099 consists of two subseries: Arlene Blum materials and Ludwig Blum materials. Arlene's subseries contains school materials, letters, diaries, articles on climbs, etc. Ludwig Blum was Arlene's father and this subseries contains photographs and draft writings.
  - Arlene Blum materials
    - Childhood (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Teen Diary (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Autobiographical material (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - John Hall: correspondence, miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Fall on Mt. Hood (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reed College: miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - MCB: Chapter 2, 1962-1966: Reed College (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Reed College (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Grad School (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1966 Mt. St. Elias Expedition (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Record of Climbs (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Ch. 3: MIT and overview (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Ch. 3: Peru (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Ch. 3: Berkeley in the 60's (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - RCS [Rock Climbing Section] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - British Columbia (Waddington 1969) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Denali letters (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Denali letters prep (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Faye Kerr (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Arlene Blum: Denali Diary (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Dana's Diary (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Grace Hoeman rescue (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Grace Hoeman (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Denali misc. info (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Denali (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Denali articles (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - St. Elias 1971 with Alice Culbert (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Endless Winter [EW] Preparation (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Ethiopia (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Uganda (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Blum: Round-the world Diary (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Joel's diary (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Letters Endless Winter [EW] (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - M. Ashraf (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Endless Winter [EW] after (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Articles (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Ch 5 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Book Proposal (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Editors (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - correspondence (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Permission Letters (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Breaking Trails [BT] drafts (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Summit inteview (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Everest Diaries Arlene Blum (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 76 Everest Exp. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Boldest Dream (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Post Trip (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Dups. Everest (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Herzog/Blum/Rodarmor (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Attitudes (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Motivations (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Photos (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Maps (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Endless Winter [EW] (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Maps photocopies only (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Junko Tabei letter photos 1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - climbing articles (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Pamir Preparations (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Pamir letters (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Pamirs 1974 Article Draft (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - APB Diary (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Molly Higgins diary (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Pamir Articles (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Pamir-later (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Lenin (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Craig Hassle (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Williamson Hassle (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Trisul Prep (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Trisul Prepare History 1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Trisul letters (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - ADB Trisul diary (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Trisul articles (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Trisul Rpts (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Trisul 1975 articles drafts (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Bruce Carson (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Trisul-later (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Ch. 8 Ames (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - ABEE Logistics (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Everest Letters (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Arlene clippings (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Everest (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - AB writings poems article drafts (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Chauvinism (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Nat Geo Rowell Outside (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Bhrigupanth Diaries (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Letters Bhrigupanth (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Misc. Bhrigupanth (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Article Bhrigupanth (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Bhrigupanth Permit (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Indira Gandhi (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Hugh Swift (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Ch. 11 GHT Diary (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Great Himalayan Traverse (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - MCB Ch 13-15 1981-82 Great Himalayan Traverse Men and Women GHT (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Ch. 13 Alps (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Annapurna- A Woman's Place [n.d.] (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Annapurna- A Woman's Place second draft (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Annapurna- A Woman's Place (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - The Himalayan Treking & Travel Course/ 1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - The Himalayan TReking Course, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Treking in Nepal Course, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Back Last 1979 Lecture fliers (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Tanya (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Treasures (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Letters from famous Folks (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Proporsal for Skirt Trouble (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Maurice Herzog N Dhyrenforth (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Society of Women Geographers "SWG" (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - AB Misc. Articles (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Edits (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Misc. Articles (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Various Publications (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Misc. Articles (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Various Publications (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Various Publicatuions (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Various Publications (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Summit Publications (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Summit Publications (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Cancer Current views on cause and prevention (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Various Publications (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Forum October 1983 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Women in the Wilderness (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - The circular Dichroism study of nine species of transfer Ribonucleic acid, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - The Himalayan Treking & travel course (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Various Postcards (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - AB articles written by AB (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - A Woman's Place is on top,1977 flag (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Brochure redesign (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Various Publications (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Various Publications (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Anna Misc: photographs (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Annap. & MTG Publicity: photographs (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Treking Misc.: photographs (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - GHT Publicity: photographs (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Arlene Blum Pictures: photographs (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - AB Misc.: photographs (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Yearly datebooks, 1982-1999 (Box 11)
    - Publications: magazines (Flat-box 12, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous newsclippings (Flat-box 12, Folder 2)
  - Ludwig Blum materials
    - Ludwig Blum: miscellaneous photogrpahs (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Ludwig Blum: photograph album, ca. 1920-1930s (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Ludwig Blum: "I Saw Frankenstein Again," drafts (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Ludwig Blum: "I Saw Frankenstein Again," drafts (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Ludwig Blum: "I Saw Frankenstein Again," drafts (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Ludwig Blum: "I Saw Frankenstein Again," drafts (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Ludwig Blum: miscellaneous ephemera (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Biography notes for Ludwig and Gertrude Blum by Arlene Blum. (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Accession 2010-021
  Series 3. Accession 2010-021 includes materials relating to the Annapurna expedition, Arlene's trek across the Himalayas, drafts of Annapurna: A Women's Place, drafts of "Women in High Places: A History of Women in Mountaineering" (unpublished), diaries, articles, etc.
  - Directory of Women Climbers: (1984, 1987, 1989); The Society of Women Geographers Bulletin: (1997, 1999 - 2005); Roads Go On Forever (book) (Box 43, Items 13)
  - Calanders & appointment books, (1964-2006) (Box 44, Items 14)
  - Annapurna - Sierra Club GTS galley (Flat-box 45, Folder 1)
  - Annapurna book release - Sierra Club release/book order (oversized layout draft) (Flat-box 45, Folder 2)
  - "Triumph and Tragedy: American Women Climb Annapurna" - Arlene Blum; National Geographic Society article (oversized layout drafts) (Flat-box 45, Folder 3)
  - Event & Lecture posters (Flat-box 45, Folder 4)
  - California Legislature Assembly Certificate of Regonition - Arlene Blum, 2009 (Flat-box 45, Folder 5)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" layout drafts for publications, merchandising, advertisements; calanders, events, publications [3 folders] (Box 46, Folders 1-3)
  - Letter to W.M. Graves (National Geographic Magazine) (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Trekker responses to evaluation sheet (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Photography - Science (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Great Himalayan Traverse Miscellaneous (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - H.S. GHT article (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - GHT - newspaper/magazine proposal (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - GHT - correspondence (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - GHT - treks & trekkers (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - GHT - maps (Box 47, Folder 9)
  - GHT - food (Box 47, Folder 10)
  - GHT - equipment (Box 47, Folder 11)
  - GHT - Nepal (Box 47, Folder 12)
  - GHT - Bhutan (Box 47, Folder 13)
  - GHT - India (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - GHT - medical kit (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - GHT Equipment: shipping plans (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - GHT brochure (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Post-trek letter of thanks, asking for newsletter items (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - GHT questionairre (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Paid receipts (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Letter to trekkers with first newsletter (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Request for newsletters (Box 48, Folder 9)
  - Complete sets of newsletters (Box 48, Folder 10)
  - Maps (Box 48, Folder 11)
  - Orders processed sheets (Box 48, Folder 12)
  - Pre-trek press release (Box 48, Folder 13)
  - Letters (Box 48, Folder 14)
  - Letters proposing series of articles on GHT (Geo, Backpacker) (Box 48, Folder 15)
  - Leter asking for food support - Oregon Freeze Dry, Inc. (Box 48, Folder 16)
  - "Dear Mountaineering Store" letter (Box 48, Folder 17)
  - Returned mail (Box 48, Folder 18)
  - Letter from people who responded to New York Times article about the GHT (Box 48, Folder 19)
  - Evergreen State (Box 48, Folder 20)
  - Arlene's "Dear Friend" letter (Box 48, Folder 21)
  - "Dear Friend of Friend" letter (Box 48, Folder 22)
  - Proposals for magzine articles (Box 48, Folder 23)
  - Book proposal (Box 48, Folder 24)
  - GHT - newsletter flats (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - GHT - newsletter negs/contatcs (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Climbing records (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - Linda's chapter (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Book correspondence (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Drafts: chapters 2-4 (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Tape transcripts (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - Tape transcripts (written) (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - AAJ article (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - miscellaneous book papers (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - printed booklet (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - chapter intros with comments (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Flyer drafts - post-climb book marketing (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - drafts: intro, epilogues, references (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - drafts: diary entries, interviews (Irene Miller) (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - "Women in High Places: A History of Women in Mountaineering" - book drafts [10 folders] (Box 51, Folders 1-10)
  - "Women in High Places: A History of Women in Mountaineering " - Elizabeth LeBlond files [2 folders] (Box 52, Folders 1-2)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - various book drafts [3 folders] (Box 52, Folders 2-5)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - drafts, chapters 1-17 [17 folders] (Carton 53, Folders 1-17)
  - Arlene's Diaries, (8/27/1978 - 11/1/1978) [2 folders] (Box 54, Folders 1-2)
  - Diaries (not Arlene's), (8/27/1978 - 11/1/1978) [2 folders] (Box 54, Folders 3-4)
  - "Women in the Himalaya" - chapter drafts [5 folders] (Box 55, Folders 1-5)
  - Book drafts & diary excerpts [2 folders] (Box 55, Folders 6-7)
  - "Prospects": Ladies' Alpine Club Year Book, (1931) - drafts (Box 55, Folder 8)
  - Letters from fans (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - Friend correspondence (Box 56, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, (1980's) (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - Luree Miller (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous letters & mailing lists (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - Contact lists (Box 56, Folder 6)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - complete book draft [2 folders] (Carton 57, Folders 1-2)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - miscellaneous drafts & notes (Carton 57, Folder 3)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - Introduction through Chapter 14 drafts [17 folders] (Carton 57, Folders 4-20)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - various chapter drafts & notes (Carton 57, Folder 21)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - diary excerpts [2 folders] (Carton 57, Folders 22-23)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - quotation ideas & correspondence (Carton 57, Folder 24)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - book critiques & responses from peers (Carton 57, Folder 25)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - published samples of complete book (Carton 58, Folder 1)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - book drafts; includes Table of Contents through Epilogue [20 folders] (Carton 58, Folders 2-21)
  - "Triumph and Tragedy on Annapurna" - National Geographic Magazine article drafts [3 folders] (Carton 58, Folders 22-24)
  - Arlene Blum interview with Joan Firey & diary excerpts (Carton 58, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous publications - magazines, books, travel brochures, club newsletters, etc.; includes some of Arlene's published articles (Carton 59, Items 46)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - Arlene Blum; published paperback copy of book; autographed (Box 60, Item 1)
  - "Annapurna: A Women's Place" - Arlene Blum; 20th Anniversary Edition published paperback copy of book; autographed (Box 60, Item 2)